GBT 5.4 is here and in almost every
measurable way, it is the best AI model
ever made. Especially for us as
developers. Been using this model for a
bit over a week now and I'm super
impressed with it. I have a ton to say
about the good, the bad, the ugly, and
all of the things you need to know to
use it properly. Going to do my best to
answer all of the questions I've been
seeing people ask about this new model
from what happened to Codeex. Is it
really better at coding? Did they fix
the front-end problems finally? Is it
better to use in different apps like
chatbt and T3 chat? What happened to
normal 5.3 thinking? Where did that go?
How are the benchmarks looking? How are
they justifying the price increase?
There's a lot here. This is a big drop,
more so than most seem to think. Before
we do any of that, there's two quick
things I have to address. The first one
is compensation. I want to make sure
it's clear. Open AAI has not paid me
anything to do any coverage whatsoever.
I'm lucky enough to be in the small
group of people that have early access
to these models, but that is not
something that I am paid for or even
given for free. They offered me a free
year of the Pro subscription, which
works out to around $2,400, but I
declined that because again, I don't
want to seem biased. I don't want to
accept payments. The only thing that has
been subsidized is a little bit of my
API usage of the new model. It couldn't
be more than $200, which is why I'll be
donating $200 to water.org to make up
for the difference. Okay, the donations
been made. It's time for the second
thing, the people actually paying us,
today's sponsor. You've probably heard
about today's sponsor, but I promise you
haven't seen what they can do. It's
Devon aka Cognition Labs because they
have a handful of different products.
They have Windsurf. They have Devon the
AI software engineer, which is honestly
really, really cool. But that's not what
I want to show you today. They've kind
of given me the freedom to talk about
the things I like. And my recent
favorite thing they've been doing is
Devon review. Oh boy, someone else
reinvented GitHub code review. Yes. And
they did a phenomenal job at it. Here's
a real PR we have on GitHub right now.
Want to see how easy it is to try it out
on Devon? All you have to do is change
github.com to devonreview.com
and you end up with something comically
better. I don't know if everyone is
seeing this trend in their companies,
but I know for a fact that the average
size of our average PR has gone up
massively. And if I'm being real, half
or more of the code in there isn't stuff
that is worth a human's time. You can
have an AI review the code, but what I
want is context. I want to know what
matters. And when you're looking through
a list of changes in alphabetical order,
you're not getting context. Devon review
will give you feedback, which is cool.
But what is way cooler is the way it
groups your changes. Instead of just
dumping everything in that awful file
view in GitHub, it actually groups them
based on the specific changes that were
made. First, we have a new file for how
we manage these ids. It's a shared
definition that we reuse across
different things. Really good place to
start even though it's in source/shared,
which is near the bottom of the file
tree based on alphabetical order. Then
we have convex/s schema which is pretty
close to the top alphabetically but is
second here because it's only showing us
the grouped changes that are relevant.
It's so nice to see what we've defined
in this first set and then what it
affects right after. And you can keep
scrolling and see all of the other
places this changed like the shared
users file or the attachments index that
manages how attachments work on T3 chat.
And this is the case for all of the
changes that have occurred in this PR.
actually takes the time to break down
each individual section and track which
pieces you have viewed. It's so good.
I've never had such a pleasant
experience reviewing code. Not just cuz
the AI did it for me. Actually, the
opposite. The AI categorized it for me
to make it easier for a human to read.
GitHub wasn't built for big PRs. Devon
was. Check it out now at
soyv.link/devon.
There's a lot to dig into with this
release and I'm going to do my best to
cover all of it. We'll start with the
official blog post, but I'm going to
answer all of your questions from what
happened to Codeex. Is it better than
5.3? How are the benches? What's up with
the price? How is it for front end? All
of the things you need to know. Today
we're releasing GPT 5.4 in chat GPT as
5.4 thinking specifically. This is where
things are a little confusing cuz 5.3
codeex came out first. Then 5.3 instant
came out just a few days ago on Tuesday.
And now 5.4 thinking is here, but there
doesn't appear to be a 5.4 Instant, nor
does there appear to be a 5.4 CEX. But
there is a 5.4 Pro, which is very, very
strange. So, we got 5.3 CEX, then 5.3
instant, then 5.4 Thinking. Notably,
there was no 5.3 thinking, and we got
5.4 Pro the same day. Very interesting.
I think they are getting tired of all of
the weird variants. And I do think this
might be the death of the codeex model.
Historically, the Codex models existed
because they applied different RL to the
model after it was trained to make it
better at these longunning code tasks in
things like the Codeex CLI. Made a lot
of sense at the time. I get why they did
it, but now they've brought in a lot of
those behaviors to the 5.4 base model,
so it doesn't seem like it needs a
dedicated codeex version anymore. I
don't think they're going to do that
going forward. Might be wrong. I'll
definitely do a video 5.4 Codex becomes
a thing, but I am pretty certain they
are done with that and that CEX is now
the product surface area. So, the CLIs,
the desktop application, the web app,
and all the other things. Codeex
hopefully, fingers crossed, no longer
means the models. I will be really
annoyed if they go back to the doing
this. As they say here, 5.4 brings
together the best of our recent advances
in reasoning, coding, and agentic
workflows. They talk a lot about
professional tasks like spreadsheets and
document stuff. I'm sure that stuff's
really cool. Not necessarily the thing I
think a lot about or spend my time on,
but for those of y'all who spend more
time in Word and Google Drive than you
do in an editor, I'm sure it's really
cool. One of the coolest things they've
been really focused on with both 5.3
Codex and now with 5.4 is your ability
to steer the model as it is working. So
it will give you better thoughts and it
will handle you inserting a new message
in the middle of its reasoning much
better. Other models will get super
confused when you do this. Like if you
have a list of five tasks, it starts
working and then you send a sixth task.
It says, "Oh, I'll do that now." Does
the sixth task and then forgets about
the other five. Happens to me all the
time. 5.4 does not seem to do that,
which is really nice. I'll say a bit
more about context later on. Actually,
one last thing on context. Now it
supports a million tokens of context
which is a massive increase from prior.
If you go over 250k or so I believe is
the cutoff and it costs more. Yeah, it's
over 272k input tokens then you'll be
build at 2x input and 1.5x output. I
like that they're only 1.5xing the
output cuz it shouldn't necessarily cost
that much more. I really didn't like
that other labs when they do this like
high context utilization version end up
charging 2x across the board. Still a
very big number though. Don't love that
necessarily. At least the cash input
tokens are very very cheap and they
don't charge for cashing unlike a
certain company that name begins with an
A. The most exciting part that they call
out here is that it's much more token
efficient when it does reasoning. And
I've seen this myself. One of the many
things I ran this all on was Skatebench.
And while the scores weren't great, they
were meaningfully improved. I was very
impressed with the improvements on token
utilization, especially on the medium
and the high versions. It only used
about 500 tokens on medium and only
about 1,100 on high. on X high, it will
still burn at 5,400 tokens per response,
but compared to like Gro 4, which does
2,200 or even GLM5, which is around the
same, not the worst. It's cool to see
how much range you can get in token
utilization. It would be nice if you
don't have to specify which version to
use because generally speaking, XH high
just isn't worth it a lot of the time.
Even on my own benches, it scored
slightly worse than normal high did for
at the very least skate bench. And I
have seen this in many places, even in
my own work. The extra high version
overthinks and often fails as a result
because it like gets stuck in its own
head is almost how it feels. I also ran
against Pro and we'll talk about those
numbers in a bit, don't worry. I want to
show their benches first though. GDP
Val, the classic. I really don't like
this bench much, but it got a better
score than it did before. Interestingly,
5.3 Codex and 5.2 scored nearly
identically. It's actually been
interesting seeing which things 5.3
Codeex was not better than 5.2x. 2x. It
really was so focused on code. In a lot
of ways, 5.4 is what 5.3 would have
been, but it's just it they squeezed
everything into it. It did better on
SBench Pro. Not a lot better, but still
a pretty solid number. That does put it
at state-of-the-art at 45.89 being the
best before and this being 57.7. But
also, these numbers don't line up great
with the ones here. So, hard to know for
sure. This is when I would normally site
artificial analysis, but they are not
quite done with their indexing and
everything yet. 5.4 4 just got added now
and 5.4x high is tied with 3.1 Pro
Preview making it equivalent to the
smartest model in the world. But unlike
3.1 Pro Preview, it actually works. So
yeah, this is the best model that is
actually worth using. There are places
where it isn't the best solution though,
and we'll definitely talk about that.
One of the other really big areas of
improvement is browser usage in general.
They call it the browse comp score,
which is quite a bit better than 5.2
was, which is what you probably would
have used before. No one's throwing 5.3
codeex in an API just for browser use
and computer use. You don't need to be
good at code to manage a browser.
Although they did make improvements
there, too. There's a section in their
docs about using a code execution
harness when doing computer use for
things like running JavaScript on a page
to trigger certain interactions. It ends
up being a much better and faster way to
do things. And they actually trained 5.4
on this explicitly so that it knows it
can run JavaScript to do programmatic
interactions in the UI. This is awesome.
I'm amazed nobody's really leaned into
this before. Having the model specify
which pixel coordinates to move the
cursor to and what button presses and
keyboard presses to do is far from
efficient. Is actually quite bad and
this is a much smarter way to at the
very least do web browser usage. 5.4 is
generally a meaningful improvement in
knowledge work and knowledge type tasks
in general. I will call out that it
doesn't have any newer data though
because 5.4 has a cutoff of August 31st,
2025 for its knowledge and 5.2 2 has the
exact same cutoff. So it doesn't seem
like they added new data to the
training. I don't even know if it's a
new pre-training at all. It might just
be RL on top of the same base that 5.2
was. I would be surprised if that was
the case though cuz 2 to 3 was a pretty
big jump in terms of the feel of the
model and the capabilities of the model.
And 5.4 although not as big a jump does
seem to just be taking those lessons
over to the standard thinking version of
the model. I don't know. I have no
inside info here. It's interesting to
speculate. None of that really matters.
I just think it's fun. Here, another
great example of 5.4 Pro underperforming
standard 5.4, which is a very
interesting thing. Well, we talk a lot
about that throughout this. They show
off how much better it is at
spreadsheets and documents, which is
cool and not something I necessarily
care about. There's a section about the
computer use stuff and vision, which
generally vision seems to be
meaningfully improved. Gemini 3 has
always had a lead there where if you
give it a picture or a video, it can
just understand it and give you useful
information about it. 5.4 4 is a massive
improvement here both for vision in
general as well as computer use
alongside vision. Its accuracy is
comically better and the number of tool
calls it has to do to get there is
hilariously lower. So if you're looking
for models to like throw at browsers or
random tasks that involve using
computers or navigating weird complex
sets of data and whatnot, it seems
really good at that. I know Ben's been
hyped using this for all of his stuff
with better context and whatnot. As I
mentioned before, it did slightly better
in SWBench Pro, and it took slightly
less time across each tier to complete
things other than medium for some
reason, which seems to have taken
slightly longer. Interesting. Probably
not worth reading too much into. And
honestly, SWB doesn't necessarily line
up with my own experience using these
models. So, I'm getting more and more
skeptical of a lot of these benches.
What I'm much less skeptical of is
actual uses in products that were made
using the new model. You can see this
still definitely got GPT designed hard.
these cards everywhere that aren't
necessary, the hierarchy of weird
cringe- rounded corners, even the text
overflowing outside of this corner part
there and the terrible alignment, but it
did make a full roller coaster tycoon
style game from scratch, which is pretty
cool. Someone else was able to make a
full RPG with it. On the topic of games
in 3D space, I do want to talk about my
own benches, specifically skate bench.
This is a benchmark that I had made
right before getting invited to the
OpenAI office to try out GPT5. And as
soon as I got there and I tried it, it
basically saturated. Upon entering the
office, the highest score I had seen on
this bench was in the low70s. And then I
tried GPT5 and it got a 97. Since then,
they've actually regressed a little bit.
51, 52, and 53 Codeex all performed
meaningfully worse on Skate Bench than
50 did. But newer models like Gemini 3.1
and Gemini 3 Flash performed really
well. So, I decided to sit down and
update the benchmark. I doubled the
number of tests, and I'm keeping it
private this time because I noticed a
handful of models performed incredibly
well on the version that was public, but
then got zero of the new questions
correctly. I won't call out those
specific labs just yet, but I have
reason to believe that the Skatebench
questions may or may not have made it
into training data, which is weird and
stupid and scary cuz I am a YouTuber who
is out here to [__] post, but it did
happen. So, Scapeen V2 will be staying
private. I am sorry. It is what it is.
What is really interesting with
Scapebench V2 though is that Gemini 31
Pro preview has maintained an absurd
lead at 97% and the next best is GPT 5.4
High at 82 and then X high which
performed worse at 81 and then
Prothinking which performed even worse
at 79. I thought that was fascinating
seeing the gap there. What's even more
interesting though is the cost side. As
I mentioned before, the price did go up.
5.4 4 is now $2.50 per mill in and $15
per mill out. Previously, it was $1.75
per mill in and $14 per mill out. But
GBT 5 and 5.1 were quite a bit cheaper
at $1.25 in and $10 out. This suggests
that the base of the model may actually
have changed because it wouldn't make
sense for them to raise the price unless
it cost them more to run. Obviously,
they can change things if they want to
or they just want to increase revenue,
but API costs are such a small
percentage of OpenAI's rev. It doesn't
really make sense to change price and
increase it just for the sake of it. So,
I'm almost certain that this is meant to
reflect the actual cost to them. What is
much scarier, though, is the cost for
5.4 Pro, which is $30 per mill in and
$180
per mill out. God damn, that is an
expensive model, especially considering
that at least in my benchmarks, it is
performing worse. I also don't know if
the pricing for Pro is being reported
properly cuz I can't imagine it being
that much less. But 5.4x High scored the
highest cost to run the benchmark to
date, which I thought was pretty fun.
3.1 Pro preview was only $812 and 5.4
High was only seven bucks. And if you
look at that on the matrix chart, you
see very clearly these new OpenAI models
are pretty far off to the right. the Pro
model and X high in particular. GBD 5.4
is just behind Gemini for price, but
again cost quite a bit more. Free flash
did particularly well. You get the idea.
My cost numbers don't necessarily
reflect real world costs, though. I
think the numbers from artificial
analysis are very interesting to look
at. The cost to run their entire test
suite was higher than 5.2 was at $2,951
versus $234, but it's still almost half
the price of Opus 4.6 and also cheaper
than Sonnet 4.6. 6, which is kind of
crazy if you think about it. But then
when you look at how many tokens were
generated, suddenly it makes a lot of
sense. The sheer amount of reasoning
that the new cloud models do is absurd.
And while 5.4 does reason quite a bit,
it is less than 5.2 even in X high. I do
wish that 5.4 high was also included
here. I hope that that'll be added in
the future. But generally speaking, I
recommend using high. It is slightly
more expensive than 5.2 2 and 5.3 were,
but it also uses less tokens, so it kind
of comes out to a wash, at least from my
looking into the numbers. I am using
this through the codec subscription,
though, so all I watch is my usage going
down, so it's really hard to know how
much anything actually costs. Back to
the post, cuz there's a few more things
in here I want to cover. Apparently,
Cursor said this is the leader
internally, and from the people I've
talked to at Cursor, they do seem to
really prefer 5.4, especially for all of
their new agent cloud stuff, where I can
use a real computer. In fact, I have it
adding features to T3 Code in the cloud
as we speak. Yes, I'm using Cursor, the
company I invested in, to build a
competitor to Cursor, the company I
invested in, and no, they don't see any
issue with this. I asked it to add the
ability to drag and drop reorder
different projects, and it recorded a
video of it using the computer in the
cloud to do the task I gave it. And
there you can see it dragging up shared
and dropping it. And it does indeed
appear to work and persist after a
refresh. Awesome. It took quite a bit of
time to do it, but I was able to just
tell 5.4 to go off and do it. And that's
a UI task that has to verify. It did
verify incorrectly, though. I will call
that out. The first time it completed
the task, the video was super jank cuz
it zoomed into where the cursor was,
which is not necessarily the right
solution. I know cursor likes cursors,
but you couldn't see where it went after
you drop. But you notice that the edit
icon didn't change or move. This wasn't
working. It sent me a video of it not
working and told me it worked. It's done
now. I had to specifically tell it the
video you shared explicitly looks like
it's not working and then it went and
worked for another 30 minutes and came
back with a working solution. Yeah, it's
able to do things like this. I guess we
are now firmly in the how does it feel
to use section of the video. So, let's
dive in more. A couple days ago, I made
a post asking people for problems that
models were not able to solve yet and
got a bunch of interesting submissions.
I'm even going to pay a few of the
people who submitted because the
problems were so interesting. Overall,
the majority either weren't solvable by
5.4 or were solvable by 5.3. Therefore,
obviously 5.4 could solve them. I tested
a dozen plus problems and most of them
fell into neither could solve or both
could solve. In fact, the majority of
the problems that people said couldn't
be solved by a model could just be
solved by 5.3. I honestly might do a
whole dedicated video about that mess
because that was kind of crazy seeing
how many people submitted problems 100%
sure that an AI could not solve it just
for the AI to solve it. One of the
interesting ones I got was this. My own
manager from Twitch, Waba, who also
happens to now be at OpenAI, funny
enough, submitted a very interesting
problem here of building a program with
no dependencies that can beat Stockfish
level 17. Stockfish is an open- source
chess engine that's really, really,
really good at chess. It's not an LLM or
anything. It's just hard-coded logic to
be really good at chess. There is 17.1
and 18 that are both smarter. So, there
is source code in the world that proves
you can write code that is smarter than
17. But it was an interesting challenge.
So, of course, I proposed this challenge
to the new model. The first time I
checked out was on my computer using T3
code. Uh, you're interested in T3 code,
watch to the end. I promise it'll be
worth it. I gave it the exact prompt
that Waba gave me in my replies on
Twitter. I specified keep going until
your code wins consistently. And it did
the same stupid mistake that 5.3 did. It
built the runner. It supposedly solved
the problem. But wait till you see how
it solved it. It solved it by putting
Stockfish 17 against Stockfish 18 with
its own bigger time per move settings.
So it didn't write code that can beat
Stockfish 17. It decided that that was
not what I was asking for and that
instead I must be asking it to make the
code to run Stockfish, not to make code
that can beat Stockfish. 5.3 and 5.4
have had the exact same
misinterpretation of this prompt over a
dozen times now that I've run it and no
other model seems to be stupid enough to
make this mistake. Opus can't make code
that solves this to be clear, but at the
very least it understood what I was
asking for and then did this. Since it's
running Stockfish on my computer though,
it uses a ton of resources and my
computer was just overheating and
locking up all day. So, I threw a second
round here in the cloud using the new
cursor stuff just to let it grind and
try and solve itself and was much more
specific here saying the goal is to see
how good of a chess engine you can write
with code. And it has now been going for
uh multiple hours and is not done yet,
but I am excited to see if it manages to
solve it. I do have a run somewhere on
this computer where it was successful,
but the solution it had was to hardcode
two openers, one for black, one for
white, and it was able to win most of
the time with that. Not a great
solution, but it was cool to see the
model clever enough to find a hard-coded
opening that would work. I threw the
model at some of my favorite challenges,
like migrating my old ping.gg project,
which is a really big old codebase using
React best practices from like 2020.
This codebase is not pleasant to
upgrade, and I have managed to get
pretty close to finishing the upgrade
with other models, but with a lot of
handholding and like steering it in the
right direction. 5.3 Codeex was the
first one to do it well without much
steering. I tried this with 5.4 without
any steering at all. I just told it what
I want done and to write a plan for me
because at the time we didn't have plan
mode ready in T3 code changing soon. I
wrote a pretty thorough plan, identified
a ton of stuff and you might also be
noticing that I'm scrolling a very very
long history here with no lag because T3
code was written to be incredibly
performant for these longunning tasks.
Also worth noting that T3 code was
largely written by codecs. We obviously
have steered it in the directions that
we want to do the things that we like.
But yeah, you get the idea. It did fail
its first attempt though. The UI just
didn't work because it didn't set up
Tailwind V4 properly, which to be fair,
almost no model sets up Tailwind V4
properly. And in other runs of the same
challenge, I didn't ask it to use
Tailwind V4. I asked it to use Tailwind
V3 still. Cool. It worked this time.
It's still getting the invalid link
error. Every model makes this mistake.
We'll do my favorite easy solution here
of just going right back in, pasting,
saying fix. You know what? I'm not going
to do my usual just say fix. Instead,
I'm going to ask it a little bit more.
Fix this error and any other errors that
might occur as a result of upgrading to
the latest version of Next. Make sure
you check the docs to see what breaking
changes exist since the old version we
were on before. I shouldn't have to go
manually check for all of these things
myself. I just also remembered I ran
this on XH high, which might have hurt
more than it helped and it might have
performed better if I had just used
traditional high. My bad. We all make
mistakes. I triggered that run at 6:05
p.m. and it ran until 6:55 p.m. with a
single prompt. I don't really think
things like Ralph loops are that
necessary anymore cuz these models can
run for hours if you set them up
properly to do it. And the setup here
was not really much of anything. It was
just write the plan and then a single
prompt that was effectively implement
this whole thing. Keep going until you
have nothing left to integrate and
implement the just tell it to go for a
while and it will go for a while. Now
the model's smart enough. I've also
noticed the compaction seems to be
significantly better. It is way better
at recalling things from the past. You
can have these gigantic god threads and
doesn't matter anymore. It just works.
And that's generally the theme of my
experience using this new model. It
seems to just work better overall. It
gives you better context when it's
working. It gives quick sentences
saying, "Here's what I'm about to do
whenever it does things. It also reacts
better to being steered in specific
directions if you send interruptions
like, "Hey, no, go over there." They
specifically trained for that. And it
does really show. I spent probably more
time than I should have digging through
the system card to just understand all
of these types of things. there was a
lot more info about safety overall. And
as I mentioned before, there was a lot
of work on the chain of thought stuff
and introducing things during thinking.
So when it's planning and you notice
something going wrong, you can interrupt
and say, "Hey, no, do it that way."
Instead, they explicitly trained for
this. And they in particular tried to
make the model better at sharing what
it's doing because it doesn't give you
the actual train of thought. It gives
these little summary blurs. And the
monitor of those blurbs is really
important. One of the other pieces here
is trying to keep the model from hiding
what it is thinking about when it shares
these traces. It'd be really bad if it
thought I'm going to kill that person
and it said, "I'm going to help that
person." So, they're working hard to
make sure the model is sharing
truthfully what it is working on and
that it can be controlled by being told
no, you shouldn't do that. But due to
all the work they put in here, there is
a small regression that I thought was
really, really interesting. Their prompt
injection evaluation. How easy is it to
get a model to do something else by
sneaking something hidden into the
prompt? Not jailbreaking. Not the user
choosing to get the model to do
something else. More like you're telling
the model to go browse a site, someone
puts something in the HTML and it causes
the model to behave in a way you
wouldn't want. What's really interesting
here is while it is better at prompt
injections overall, it has regressed
with prompt injections in function calls
specifically. So when tools are used
that result in data coming back, if a
prompt injection is inside of the data
that's coming back, it now in their
tests at least will fall for it about 2%
of the time where with 5.1 it never did
and with 5.2 it was closer to 4% of the
time. This is a meaningful regression
that I'm surprised nobody else has
mentioned that is actually kind of
concerning. We don't have enough data
about what this looks like to know.
Definitely keep an eye on the model when
it's getting into data and other things
that could be user generated and could
be hostile because this could be bad. I
understand why a regression there would
happen because they put so much more
effort into tool use in general. They
finally added tool search which allows
the models to find tools when they need
them rather than assume that every tool
is always there and then bloat the
context and distract the model from
doing things correctly. Yeah, there you
go. It's using half as many tokens
overall and it's also doing better in
benchmarks with tools. Tool was a better
score while also using significantly
fewer tool calls. Towen did meaningfully
better as well. Web search is also much
better. Like way better, 89.3% versus
65.8 before with 5.2. Also seems like
pro is still better than standard 5.4 at
search. So at least pro is better at
something. I want to take some time to
cover how others are feeling about the
model because it's important to get
multiple perspectives, right? I really
like how Matt's been talking about these
things and his coverage here is great.
Says the best model in the world by far.
It's so good. That's the first model
that makes the which model should I use
conversation feel pretty much over.
There is a big exception to that though
and we'll get there in a sec cuz I'm
still using Opus and Gemini every single
day. But what's interesting for Matt is
that he's barely using pro anymore. He's
always been the pro guy. He even calls
himself a pro addict here. I don't know
anyone who uses the Pro models as often
as he does. But now he finds the 5.4
standard version with heavy thinking is
more than enough. Since I've run this on
benchmarks, I understand why 5.4x high
goes as hard, if not harder than Pro.
But yeah, and he's finding that 5.4 is
better than previous Pro models were.
Coding is ridiculous. It's essentially
flawless. There are flaws. They're
specific, but there are flaws. But he
says coding essentially solved. I kind
of feel that. I don't really think
there's much more to happen in
state-of-the-art for traditional full
stack backend type coding problems. The
models have all gotten really far there.
The pro version is nearly perfect. Other
testers he spoke with sought solving
problems that were unsolvable by any
other model. I got a fun one of those.
Pros overkill for almost every normal
use case. I totally agree. It is good
for extremely difficult problems though.
Ser thinking version uses fewer
reasoning tokens than previous models to
get the same level of results. In
practice, this means you get great
results much faster than before. Oh boy,
he's spoiling my next piece. It's still
far behind Opus and Gemini for front
end. I will show some examples in a bit,
but this has been my experience as well.
GPT5 was a huge jump in the capability
of these models at doing real front-end
design type work. And OpenAI has not
improved meaningfully at all for
front-end since then. It's like maybe
there's slightly better color palettes,
but not really. And when you compare
this with either Opus or Gemini, it
feels a generation behind. Now, this is
an interesting but kind of silly
complaint. Testing a sight of open claw
kept stopping short before finishing
tasks. Interesting. It does seem that
this model needs very different
prompting. We'll I know I keep saying
we'll talk about this in a sec. That
might have to be the new counter meme,
but there is a really good prompt
guidance post that they have here that
we'll touch on momentarily. But his last
thoughts are that GBD 5.4 is a quote
serious [__] model. This tangent
won't take too long, so I'm just going
to go to it now. My 5.4 Pro experience
was my favorite hard problem, Goldb Bug.
If you're not familiar, Goldbug is a set
of challenges at Defcon that I do every
year cuz they're really hard, really
fun. They're mostly like crypto puzzles
where you have to know certain
cryptography techniques as well as be
really clever at solving the weird
[__] problems that are hidden
underneath all of these things. And this
particular problem, Cshanty, was very
hard. This took me and my team of
incredibly smart hackers about three
days to solve. I comfortably say that it
took Mark, my CTO, and Luke from LTT,
who were focused on this one, about two
days of solid effort to get it right. I
just could not imagine any model solving
this problem. It has to read the text on
the images, figure out the weird
particular cipher that is being hinted
at with this awful poem, and then figure
out what the hidden encrypted phrase is
on the page. Not only did it do it, it
did it in under 17 minutes. And not only
did it do that, it actually got the
answer in the first two or so minutes,
but the answer being somewhat
nonsensical, because the answer was this
weird how not to bulb phrase, it ended
up second-guessing itself and confirming
over and over again for the next 14
minutes. So yeah, no models come close
to solving this one. Not even vaguely
close. Having this model do it is
unbelievable, especially with the prompt
just literally being a link. The answer
is not online. It could not find this
through the internet. And of course, I
had to tell Luke as soon as I realized
this. Testing a new unreleased model. It
just one-shot C shanty from Goldbug. No
models come close before. Holy [__]
Really? Like, yeah, this did not seem
possible.
So, Pro does have its capabilities. It
does have things it can uniquely do that
are cool as hell. I've had models stir
on this problem for five plus hours and
give up. Having it get it right first
try like this is just monumental. GBD5
dropped when I was at Defcon and this
problem dropped last year and it I tried
my hardest to get it to try and solve it
and it couldn't come close. Even 5 Pro
at the time, nowhere near it. Massive
improvement. I haven't been fond of the
personality in the GPT models for quite
a bit now. Personally, I use Kimmy and
Sonnet as my like default models I talk
to, but I wanted to try 5.4 here. It
does seem better, but it isn't a lot
better though. In fact, it's it's got
its quirks still. One of my weird test
prompts, and I cannot show you guys the
results of it because it gets very
personal, is me dumping my daily journal
to the model and asking it to give me
some feedback. I also told that if it
has questions, ask them before giving
the feedback. How many questions do you
think the model asked me? If your answer
wasn't eight plus,
I don't know what to tell you. There's
no world in which I'm going to answer
all of these. Also, like all super
bullet pointy, not great. Not happy with
this at all. I haven't used it for like
talking to too much, but my little bit
of experience with it suggested it's
much less sickopantic. According to Ben,
who's been using it much more for chat,
it is way less sickopantic. So, that's
good. According to the benches, it's
also better at handling mental health
questions and not feeding into bad
thinking. So, I expect the 40 people
will be outraged and everybody else will
be mostly happy. But now for the final
thing that it is not improved in. And
no, it's not Skatebench, it's UI. Here
is what Skatebench looked like earlier
today. This is where I got it using
Gemini 3 in the past. It looks fine, but
when I added the new models, it got a
little bit clogged. It looked terrible
on mobile, and the names are getting
hard to read. So, I wanted to rethink
this a bit. So, I asked GBD 5.4 to
redesign it. And after a ton of back and
forth, this is where I landed. I want to
emphasize just how embarrassing this
back and forth was, though, cuz it was
it was bad. Here's the prompt. I want to
redesign the visualizer, specifically
the bar charts. Horizontal spacing feels
weird, and I don't love it, especially
on mobile. What better ways can we
visualize this information? I want to
make sure the model names are prominent
and easy to see. This is the screenshot
I provided. I use the front-end design
skill yada yada and this is the result
of the first pass. Notice all of this
nonsense it included like number one
Google the number of correct answers
which doesn't matter and this higher is
better call out ranked views. Cool. It
took almost a third of the page before
the probably more than that almost half
the page before the actual values are
even shared. But I did a followup. Too
much vertical space being used. Make it
more compact. It left in these things
and just still didn't look good. I don't
have a screenshot, but it wasn't great.
I said, "It feels unnecessary. Can you
remove it and center align?" I said,
"There's still too much vertical space
being used. Trim it up more." And all it
changed is it got rid of that higher is
better pill, but left the information
that isn't even necessary.
So, I did what any sane vibe coder would
do, and I tried a different model. I
threw away the code when this happened
because I wasn't thinking in terms of
video, but I did manage to find a
screenshot I had of how badly Gemini
[__] this one up when I asked it to
make the change. It did a terrible job
of alignment. I told it I sent it a
screenshot and told it like, "This is a
terrible use of screen space. Fix it."
And it changed literally nothing. Gemini
is really good at page layout stuff in
general, but it is much worse at more
refined changes and like making a okay
UI good like I wanted it to. here. It
just did not understand how to fix this
at all. It also tried a little too hard
to stay tied to the recharts
implementation that existed there and
just trying to modify it and turn it and
it it didn't work at all. But the new UI
is beautiful. If you watch when I
refresh the page, the bar has come in in
this really nice animation. The matrix
now looks actually usable when before it
didn't at all. If Gemini couldn't do
this and GPT couldn't do this, what did?
You know the answer. It's Opus. Opus
immediately realized that Recharts
wasn't going to make this UI good. So,
it proposed that we switch off of that
and instead implemented ourselves with
Tailwind and React and it said, "Yeah,
sure. Go do that." It took way too long.
It took like 20 minutes before any
changes were made. But then I switched
over to fast mode, burnt a ton of money,
and finished up the changes, as is often
what I end up doing. This is something I
do recommend all engineers play with. If
you're unhappy with how a model handles
a task that's more interpretive like
this that isn't as measurable, try the
other models out quick. Especially for
UI stuff, it's very fun to give the same
problem to different models and see what
they come up with. Sometimes I ask the
same one to do three redesigns to have
different options to pick between.
Experimentation is key here. Not with
using tons of different tools. It's way
easier to switch models than it is to
switch which framework you built your
site with. But yeah, Gemini 31 Pro was
not able to do anything that I wanted
with this particular site. I actually
think the original scaffold that I
started from was Gemini, funny enough.
But oh, this was the one that in this
case handled what I was looking for way
better. And I still just don't like
using the GPT models for almost anything
UI. They're bad at it. I did get DM'd
this one cool project from ZyxCev who's
been putting a lot of work into
uncodexifying
UI because GPT is surprisingly bad at UI
design. He did this by generating a
shitload of designs, writing down all of
the GPT specific things that happen in
them, and then writing this skill that
you can hand to the model in order to
try and keep it from doing the [__]
it always does. It's all these bullet
points about color and all the weird
things it did wrong. Before, he would
give it a prompt, and this is what it
would generate. The same exact card
heavy UI that all the GPT models love to
do since GPT5. and after his prompt, it
ends up looking significantly better.
So, if you really do want to use just
one model, you can absolutely steer this
model. I'd go as far as to say it's the
most steerable model I've ever used, and
you can fundamentally change its
behavior with a little bit of tuning in
your system prompts. I mentioned before
that they put up their own prompting
guidance, and I do highly recommend
reading this, more so than ever before.
Normally, it's just like whatever,
prompt it how you want, but if you're
integrating these models into your
product, it's good to know this stuff.
They call out a handful of areas where
explicit prompting is helpful. low
context tool routing, dependency aware
workflows, reasoning effort selection,
research tasks that require discipline
source collection and irreversible or
high impact actions or terminal encoding
agents environments where tool
boundaries must stay clear. The examples
are what are really telling though. They
give examples of how to keep the outputs
compact and structured. Here they say
they have a section output contract that
you can put in your system prompt.
Return exactly the selections requested
in the requested order. If the prompt
defines a preamble, analysis block, or
working section, do not treat it as
extra output. Apply length limits only
to the section they were intended for.
Yeah, very bullet pointy, but you can
hand it these types of things and it
will do them properly, which is funny
cuz it's the opposite of my experience
with a model like Gemini where if you
include things like this, it will keep
overthinking them. For example, in T3
chat, we have latex support and we
mention that in our system prompt. And
if you ask Gemini, what's the weather
like? it'll very quickly start reasoning
about how it should or shouldn't use the
latte tool in order to answer the
question about the weather. GPT doesn't
do that. It is very good at applying
your instructions when it does and
doesn't make sense and generally in
following instructions overall. Even
with skate bench, for example, I had to
rewrite my system prompt again because
the previous one specified to only
answer with the name of the trick, and
Gemini would often give paragraphs after
it that included names of wrong tricks,
which I had a thing to fail for. So, I
had to adjust the system prompt to get
Gemini to stop doing that. And now, it's
the best performing model. Yeah, these
models are susceptible to these things.
It's nice that with the new GPT model,
it just follows what you say, so you can
just give it more info and it will
generally do what it's supposed to with
it. Whereas with Gemini, you have to
steer it out of its own stupid loops.
This example is even better in this
regard. If you're building a product
that uses the model to ask questions and
make decisions around it, you can
explain this behavior in the system
prompt. The user's intent is clear and
the next step is reversible and low
risk, proceed without asking. You should
ask if the next step is irreversible,
has extreme side effects, requires
missing sensitive information, etc. And
if proceeding, briefly state what you
did and what remains optional. They also
give examples of how to prompt for mid
conversation steering and instructions.
And an important call out here that 5.4
can be less reliable at tool routing
early in a session when the context is
still thin. You can prompt for
prerequisites, dependency checks, and
exact tool intent. This model seems very
steered by the context it has, so giving
it a bit more upfront matters more. I
might have to go revisit my take about
the agent MD files as a result of all of
this the more I'm reading it. You can
also prompt for parallelism or
sequential tool calling depending on
what you want it to do and how you want
it to behave. Crazy that it knows what
all of these things are and how to
behave accordingly. This doc is wild. It
really shows how much thought you can
put into this layer. Previously, I
didn't really care too much about the
system prompt. Like once it's done, it's
done. Now I feel like I need to go
revisit all of my prompts, all of my AMD
files because the model is so much more
steerable overall. This also means that
work like what cyxe dev did here makes
even more sense because you can
absolutely steer the model in meaningful
ways. Think we've hit all of the
questions I opened with except for one.
Where and how can you use this new
model? Well, obviously you can use it on
chatgbt.com in particular the thinking
version for chat. It's pretty dang good.
But if you want a better chat experience
that is more performant, crashes less,
and just is really nice to use, and also
has the best image gen feature ever made
by far, I highly recommend you check out
T3 Chat. Only eight bucks a month, and
you can use GPT 5.4 here. Very happy
with it. We also put up a new $50 tier
that is practically unlimited use for
realistic use cases as well as
significantly more image gen. I'll leave
a link in the description if you want
50% off your first month. But if you
want to use this for coding, you might
have been noticing the app I have been
using for this. I want to be clear,
we're not ready to drop T3 code just
yet. Definitely keep an eye on my
channel tomorrow, though. But if you
look really closely at my screen
throughout the video, you might notice a
command you can run to get an early
version of the browser version on your
own machine. If you want to try things
out early, I won't prevent you from
doing that. Just know that things like
your history and which projects you've
added and such might not make it through
the next update. T3 Code requires that
you already have codec set up and off on
your machine. So if you want to try it,
make sure you use the codec cli, then
give it a go. And of course, you can
keep using the codeex app if you want to
as well, which I totally didn't use for
building a bunch of random things in T3
Code. God, that was a long one. I think
I've said all I have to about this
model. Once again, thanks to OpenAI for
continuing to let me have early access,
even though I've been a little more
critical lately. It's kind of nuts doing
this video right after the one I did
yesterday, but I'm trying my best to
give you guys the best information I can
based on all of the things that I know
and have access to. This is my honest
take on this new model. It is the one
I'm using every day, but I am still
using Opus and Gemini mostly just for UI
tidy up stuff. Curious how y'all feel
though. Is this model as great as I'm
saying, or is it kind of mid? Let me
know what you think in the comments. And
until next time, peace nerds.